So this is samuta
428 translated as a horn blower. It says
on one occasion the blessed one was
staying near Nalanda in the pavarik
mango grove. Then Aibanda Caputa the
headman a disciple of the nigantas went
to the blessed one and on arrival having
bowed down he said to the
Buddha uh oh no actually sorry the
blessed one said to him headman how does
niganta nataputa teach the dhamama to
his disciples nigant nataputa teaches
the dharma to his disciples in this way
all those who take life are destined for
a state of deprivation
are destined for hell. All those who
steal, all those who engage in sexual
misconduct, all those who tell lies are
all destined for a state of deprivation
are destined for hell. Whatever one
keeps doing frequently by that one is
led. In other words, the the frequency
of one's actions determines where one is
being led to in which which rebirth,
which hell, which
consequences. That's how niganta teaches
the dharma to his disciples. So then the
Buddha said, well, if it's true that
whatever one keeps doing frequently by
that one is led, then no one will be
destined for a state of deprivation or
destined to hell. In line with those
nigant's words, what do you think headman? If a
words, what do you think headman? If a
man is one who takes life, then taking
that into consideration time spent
taking into consideration time spent
doing and not doing of taking life
whether by day or by night. Which one is
more? The time spent he the time he
spends taking on taking life or the time
he spends not taking life.
So the headman replies, "Well, yes, if a
man is one who takes life, then taking
into consideration time he spends doing
it, whether by day or by night, then the
time he spends taking life is less,
which means he more frequently abides by
not taking
life." And then it goes on to repeat
this about stealing, engaging in sexual
misconduct, lying, basically about
breaking the five
precepts. Um and then uh once the Buddha
obviously uh showed um show showed him
the the the flaw in that um in that
argument he continues says there is the
case headman where a certain teacher
holds such doctrine holds do the the
view of all those who take life are
destined for a state of deprivation are
destined for hell. All those who steal,
all those who indulge in sexual
misconduct, all those who tell lies,
they're all destined for state of
deprivation are destined for
hell. So kind of saying
that pretty much if you would have
engaged in any of these acts, you're
done. You're going to
hell. So if a disciple has a faith in
that teacher, he would then have a
thought occur to him. Um, all those who
take life are destined for a state of
deprivation or destined for hell. There
are living beings that I have killed.
Doesn't matter if it's accidental or
not. I have actually killed some living
beings. Therefore, I am destined for a
state of deprivation. I am destined for
hell. He then fastens onto that view.
And if he doesn't abandon that
conviction, he doesn't abandon that
state of mind, does not relinquish that
view, then he will be uh basically
pretty much as if carried off placed in
hell. In other words, he's heading to
hell. And then it repeats again the same
type of
um let's say fixed view for the other
remaining precepts.
And then the Buddha contrasts that with
um there is a case headman where a
tatagat appears in the world worthy of
and rightly self- awakened with clear
knowing and conduct well gone a knower
of the world unexelled trainer of those
to be tamed teacher of human and divine
beings awakened blessed he in various
ways criticizes and senses
uh censures the taking of life and says
abstaining from take abstain from taking
life abstain from stealing abstain ain
from sexual misconduct, abstain from
engaging in such sexual misconduct. He
criticizes and censores telling of lies
and says abstains from telling of
lies. A disciple has faith in him. The
blessed one is in variety of way
criticizes and sens censures the taking
of life and says abstain from taking
life. There are beings that I have
killed to a greater or lesser extent
like in this life or you could even
stretch it and say well in the past past
lives I must have done
it that was not right that was not good
I am remorseful because of that but I
cannot undo what I've done so reflecting
thus he abandons right
there abandons right then the taking of
life and in the future refrains from
taking of life this is how there comes
to be the aband abandoning of that evil
deed. So, uh this point is important
because it shows that how he abandons
the past evil deeds that he can't
change. He cannot undo what he done. But
taking on remorse of that action, he
abandons taking of life and refrains
from future taking of life. We're going
to address that later on specifically
that question. But the point is that it
is in the present now that you would
abandon both past actions that you
cannot fix anymore and future actions
that you haven't performed
yet. So it goes on saying the blessed
one in a variety of way criticizes
sensious stealing engaging sexual
misconduct telling of lies and then
repeats the same type of reflection
remorse on account of the five precepts.
And this is where I added a part from um
Agama SAMA 916
SAMA 916
um that adds kind of like a bit more
description to the same to the same
um um passage from Pali which says from
former times because of my ignorance and
lack of wisdom I had intention to kill.
Therefore now I feel remorse although I
cannot make those evil deeds cease. on
account of this remorse in the future I
shall be free from killing and likewise
free from stealing, sexual misconduct
and lying. So it quite clearly points
how on account of that remorse you
already figuratively speaking uh create
some space between you and the previous
actions of the unh wholesome kind that
you would have done. And by taking on
that remorse correctly,
uh that's how you already indicated that
in the future, well, you won't be going
in that
direction. So it says, I will then also
attain complete fulfillment of true
release of mind and the true release of
wisdom. Once those releases are
fulfilled, I will not slander the noble
right view. In other words, when he
fulfills those releases, there will be
no point uh no part of the um the right
understanding of what the practice is
that he can sort of misconceive and see
uh an obstruction as a non-obstruction
and so on like those other example in
the sutras. So by the condition of the
right view I will be born into a good
destiny and in the heavens and so on.
So, so yeah, then the polyut just kind
of sums up that having abandoned taken
life, he refrains from taking life.
Having abandoned stealing, he refrains
from stealing. Having abandoned sexual
misconduct, he refrains from sexual
misconduct. Having abandoned lies, he
refrains from lies. Having abandoned
divisive speech, he refrains from
divisive speech. Having abandoned harsh
speech, he refrains from harsh speech.
idol chatter, he refrains from idol
chatter. Uh covetousness, he becomes
uncetous. ill will, anger, he becomes
one with a mind of no ill will. Having
abandoned wrong views, he becomes one
who has right views. So all of these
were pretty much the practical
progressive developments of the body. Um
act by body, acts by speech and then
acts by mind. The the the final roots of
covetousness, ill will uh wrong views.
Um and then uh Samama here adds another
kind of as I said aspect to it. It
says oh village chief of headman these
these wise disciples uh of long hearing
practice like this at all times day and
night they observe whatever
arises. If the mind intention to kill
arises they reproach themselves saying
this is wrong this doesn't fit. If the
mind if the mind's intention to kill
does not arise, they remain without
resentment or hatred and the mind
develops friendliness. So observing
whatever arises, it's not like just
metaphysically thinking about
theoretical aspects of oh everything
arises and and then like mere
observation of stuff. No, it it
continues and tells you exactly what
what to look for. So it's the mental
intentions. So we're not even talking
about the course acts anymore. They
would have been abandoned way
beforehand. um then he trains further in looking at
um then he trains further in looking at
the mind's intentions. So if intention
to kill arises even before he allows the
proliferation of it before he starts to
carelessly feed it through the thoughts
of anger and cruelty and harm and so on.
He already recognizes that the the
intention of the level of that wild
animal on the level of that chitta and
says whoa this is already wrong this
doesn't fit. So he already puts brakes
on
that. So then if the chitta does not
have the intention to kill then he
remains without resentment or hatred.
The mind that chitta develops
friendliness and he recognizes that. So
he's not going around telling himself
everything arises or going around
reproaching his chitta for everything
and nothing. No, it's for the clear
intentions of harm, of unh wholesome, of
covetousness of ill will. He abandons
those by recognizing even intentions
towards those before they even fully
manifest as as the uh the proliferated
examples. So it says it says then the
mind then develops friendliness.
Basically when there is not even an
intention to kill or harm present in the
chitta that animal is friendly and you
know that again I always give the simile
of the of the dogs or animals. You know
when your dog is
incapable of of of biting a a stranger,
you know it has it doesn't have it in
him and and you trust it. And this will
be the same. You would have trained your
own mind, your own wild animal. And now
you trust it. You know that it cannot
even have the intention to harm, let
alone actually act out of that harm. So
then that mind is friendly. That it's a
state of friendliness regardless of who
or what comes at it.
Even if it's people provoking it, the
mind, the animal trained in friendliness
cannot become unfriendly because you
recognize the value of it. You insisted
on that training rightly and you would
have develop it through abandoning the
intentions of ill will, the intention to
kill, not through, as we're going to see
later uh random mechanical practices or
visualizations and mantras and and and
repeating phrases and so on.
So the agama continues says having
generated this joy on account of that
friendliness rapture arises with rapture
the mind becomes tranquil. So the animal
calms down even more with that calmness
with that tranqu tr tranquility it
experiences pleasure with pleasure it
becomes one becomes composed. So there
is composure. With composure the noble
disciple with the mind of friendliness
without resent resentment without
jealousy without ill will becomes broad
and limitless filling one quarter of space
limitless filling one quarter of space
with right composure. The second the
third up to the four quarters he fills
with the result of his composure on
account of abandoning even intentions to
harm, intentions to ill will, intentions
to kill.
So filling up the quarters is the pretty
much spreading the outcome. Let's put it
that way. Like the outcome goes in all
directions because it's already
unlimited. Does not mean he he he
fabricates the uh the the limitless
state of mind through traveling in all
directions and then patching them
together or something.
So then the second then the third up to
the fourth quarters throughout the
entire world in all directions with a
mind of friendliness without resentment
without jealousy without ill will broad
and limitless well cultivated pervading
all directions dwells in the right
composure. Um so Pali basically says
kind of repeats having abandoned taking
of life wrong and then he just says that
disciple of the noble ones thus devoid
of covetousness devoid of ill will
unbewilded alert mindful keeps pervading
the first direction with the mind imbued
with friendliness likewise the second
likewise the third likewise the fourth
and this is what people think aha okay
so this is what I do in order to
practice meta I keep pervading the
directions but then those same people
overlook the very
line beforehand that still confirms the
very ext expounded passage that comes
from Agama which is are you devoid of
covetousness completely devoid of
intentions of ill will completely
unconfused alert being unable to be
unmindful then yes pervade you know the
directions of east and west and so on
but this is just overlooked as aha yeah
sure and then I'll move on onto the
method of pervasion and and and all
these these practices while in reality
this line is pretty much abandoning the
five hindrances like thoroughly abandon
possibilities towards towards the unh
wholesome not just oh I'm temporarily um
not engaging in unh wholesome actions
thus I'm free from the hindrances well
that would basically put you in the very
first wrong view that the suta started
with oh I'm temporarily not engaging
therefore I'm fulfilling it it's like no
most of the times you are temporarily
not engaging with anything unh
wholesome, but you're still well within
the domain of hindrances and you cannot
claim that you're devoid that your your
your chitta your animal is devoid of
covetousness, devoid of possibility of
ill will because if something comes that
provokes it, it will very much react. So
there's nothing wrong with this parley
passage in a sense of yeah there it is
says the disciple of the noble ones i.e.
somebody with the right view already on
account of purification of his own
behavior frees himself from
hindrances and then that mind of
friendliness spreads in all four
directions all-encompassing abundant
expansive he's not doing it it's the
result of his correct setup and
withdrawal and abandonment of things one
should abandon and then it's the simile
just as a strong trumpet blower can
notify the four directions without any
difficult in the same way when the
liberation through friendliness is thus
developed to thus pursued any deed done
to a limited extent no longer remains
there no longer stays there uh we'll
address that after the after we read to
the suta like what does what that means
specifically um then it goes for the other brahma
um then it goes for the other brahma
viharas these are like the the stock uh
phrases uh pointing out that there is a
refinement to the same
principle so um friendliness
compassion, appreciation,
econity, meta, karuna,
mudaeka. Uh so in the end
Asibuta the headman was obviously very
impressed and he said magnificent lord
just as if he were to place upright what
was overturned to reveal what was hidden
to point out the way for the one who was
lost to carry a lamp into the dark um so
those with eyes could see forms in the
same way the blessed one through many
lines of reasoning made the dhamma clear
and then he went to the refuge and so
on. So
um yeah so that concludes the
suta and then the the points to consider
the questions that can be raised on account
questions that can be raised on account
of it um as I already said from that
initial nigantas point of view uh most
people most of the time already keep a
precepts and I heard it I heard it
people saying like oh do you live by
even five precepts do you live by
precepts uh it says yeah like most of
basically because most of the time I'm
not breaking
them and um I even heard monks say that
as well like in response to a question
of how to deal with like thoughts of
sensuality that come up throughout the
day and bother one who is like
restrained and living in the monastery
like the answers they were given were
like well you know most of the time you
don't go around thinking about those
things so don't worry about it and it's
like it's exactly nigantis kind of falls
into that nigantis view that um Well,
from that point of view, most of the
time you don't do most of the unh
wholesome stuff. So then what? You're
already an arhan. There is no problem at
all. So then the question that that's
that that obviously naturally poses
itself is what's the difference between
someone who can rightly say that they
keep the precepts and someone who isn't
keeping them. They just circumstantially
kind of uphold them until they break
them. And um most of you already
And um most of you already
understood from u from the previous
discussions. It's basically the
difference is whether you took them on
uh in the form of your intention, your
decision in the form of being taken on
indefinitely without a an expiry date.
Even if you break them, that's the
point. Like even if you end up breaking
the preview due to the
weakness, if you still took them on in a
indefinite sense, that can still result
in actual progress.
But if you don't take them on in a that
in that infinite or indefinite sense uh
even if you don't break them you won't
make any progress because as the agamas
um parallel to this that I included
points out you need to basically it's on
the problem is on the level of your
intention to do these things not even on
the fact that you did it or that you
might still be doing
it. So in order to get to the root to
the layer of where that intention of
mind to kill to harm to commit uh sexual
misconduct and so on you need to have
withdrawn yourself physically from it
purify the speech so that then these
mental levels can become uh apparent and
addressed. So that's why that
determination that would pertain into
infinity or I will train under the
precepts even five for that matter can
serve as as a some sort of beginning of
the training but obviously as I said
there's a big elephant in the room of
still being immersed in sensuality and
expecting your mind to grow but
hypothetically speaking taking
on even one precept but in that ultimate
sense and we'll see why is that relevant
like further down this discussion Even
in that ultimate sense, taking even one
precept brings you to the level of that
intention to then break it or not when
circumstances like sort of um create
such conditions but not taking it in
that ultimate sense. As I said, you
could be keeping all of the monk's rules
if you want and still actually not grow
on account of them.
So that that's why like even that
intention to keep the precepts that you
made beforehand even after you break
them that intention can still remain and
be picked up and that intention would be
the direct reason then for feeling
remorseful for feeling u uh regretful
responsible for your actions and so on.
Without it everything becomes sort of
negotiable in that sense and of course
central mind we all know what directions
will negotiations
lean. So then
um yes so somebody asked like can can
one say that the reflections of a
faithful disciple mentioned further in
the suta are the equivalent to taking
full responsibility for one's lives and
actions. It's on the level of oh but I
cannot do undo what I've done. So that
means one takes responsibility for the
pain of those past actions without
trying to manage them and with the
danger of acting in the future in the
same way
revealed. So that's exactly that that
exactly comes through that
responsibility of taking it on and not
justifying it. Well, I did it because I
didn't know or this or that. It's like
no no I did it full stop. Doesn't matter
why. It doesn't matter if I was coerced
in doing it. I chose to do it. I acted
out. It's on me. There's nothing that
can sort of diminish that. Um so then
obviously like that can lead you know
people could think like aha okay so I
blame myself for everything but that's
going too far the other
way. So you don't you you don't that
guilt that comes on account of
recognizing the stuff that you did.
Well, now you also need to harness that
guilt, not just feed it sort of
carelessly like a
wildfire because the point
is there are things you did that you
can't change but from now onward when
you recognize that every single thing
you are responsible for means every
single thing you could do
rightly. So that that's exactly the
point and why the Buddha contrasted that
type of reflection because that whole
view like when he said um there is a
some teacher might believe that whoever
kills or or or commits anything immoral
goes to hell and then Buddha said well
his disciples would then recognize and
say well I did that there therefore I go
to hell and if they don't change the
view of that they will go to hell
because it's basically it's like a form
of determinism. See they they say okay
so whoever kills it's done it's doomed
there is nothing he can do about it I've
killed therefore I can't do anything
about it so when they can actually do
something about it I here and now
abandon the intention for future actions
of the same kind that bind them to the
past ones as well they remain bound to
the past actions on account of their
view and because of that they go to
hell so then like how how can a person
use the remorse rightly as I said and
make sure that the future actions of
breaking the precepts are are are not
done abandoned like now you know that in
the future you won't do
it so how can you know now that you
won't break the pre in the future well
obviously that takes training you can't
just decide or figure out mentally or
theoretically and then you know for sure
um you know through training it right
now so what is it that you train right
now well for example Example, you
contemplate the worst case
scenario. So you say, I will not kill. I
might have killed. I can't change that,
but from now onwards I will never kill.
Indefinitely. I take on this precept.
Okay, great. Now add to that scenario.
How about if somebody comes and uh
attacks me? Or how about if somebody
comes and attacks my children or my wife
or things that are dear to me? How about
if somebody comes and starts stealing
things that I find important, necessary
for my
life? What's my answer there? Would I
then kill or harm or act out of ill will
because I feel justified? And if you see
your mind moving towards well, you will
already know the answer by the way. Like
you start posing those questions in a
serious manner, you will already
know where your mind is leaning toward.
you already know what it would want to
do, what the animal will want to kind of
uh perform. So then you recognize, aha,
okay, so that's not abandoned in
me. So I'm keeping the precepts now, but
it's obviously
conditional. I would like it to be
indefinite and unconditional commitment
to those principles of behavior, but my
mind rejects that idea. So what do I do?
Do I ignore it and pretend and and turn
a blind eye and pre and hope that those
scenarios will never come up in the
future. Therefore, I will remain pure in
my precepts or do I actually train the
mind so that literally even if somebody
comes in starts attacking things that
are dear to me, I will my mind will be
unable to wish it
harm. It will be unable to abandon the
the the four pervaded directions of
friendliness they would have developed.
So that is an actual contemplation.
That's like that sallea suta the what
the Buddha described what the actual
aacement is what actually burns away the
unh wholesome masters in killes it's
such reflections of others may be harm
here we won't be others may be cause
harm here we won't cause harm others may
be deceitful here we won't be deceitful
others and so it lists all these unh
wholesome things so it means that
everybody else can choose to cause harm arm for
else can choose to cause harm arm for
whatever reason rightly or wrongly
self-defense doesn't here there will be
no exception that will not be
done. So in order for that to sink into
that wild animal and become its own
value you need to train it. So you need
to keep bringing up these scenarios and
see if if the animal is wound up and
then okay leave it with that leave it
with that wound up
state until it settles and then bring it
up again until it settles and then bring
it up again and leave it until it
settles. Eventually keep bringing it
until the animal doesn't even come up.
it has actually accepted and started
seeing for itself that oh it is actually
better even in the most extreme scenario
I will be untouched by suffering if I
don't act if I act that's when the not
just present suffering will hit me but
it will connect me to everything else in
the past that I might have done so it's
a th freedom from past and future
through the reflection here and now
that's what we said that is the actual
effacement that is the actual
purification Um obviously if somebody not established
Um obviously if somebody not established
in the precepts, not established in
sense restraint, uh nowhere near the
right view starts contemplating the
worst case
scenarios, well even they if they do it
rightly could have some benefits. there
all those like um the I don't know like
half a dozen of like renowned
psychotherapy schools and stuff that use
exactly these techniques of bringing up
traumas and stuff to have your uh to
maintain the emotional non-response
towards it until it becomes a
norm. In other words, triggering sort of
uh uh memories and so on you bring up so
that you stop being triggered by it
through non-acting out. So even even
even contemporary household kind of
psychotherapists they have no intention
of abandoning the whole sphere of dooka
recognize the value in it. Now imagine
you pair that practice with the actual
precepts taken indefinitely with the
actual sense restraint taken
indefinitely. That is the aacement that
leads to complete freedom from suffering
no other
way. So and that's how you will know
what you what you won't be able to do in
the future. And I kept saying that to
people, you know, sometimes you imagine
a scenario and you get you the pressure
arises because you don't know what to
do. What would be the right thing to do?
And often people ask that what should a
Buddhist do if such and such thing
happens. It's like you're looking at it
wrongly. It's not about what to do and
figure out what you should do. It's
about being completely 100%
clear of things you will not do
regardless of the circumstances. And
also that as I said value that
recognition has had to sink down to the
cheetah as well. That's when you have
confidence that you know you you won't
act because the animal won't
act. So that's how you can you can know
what you become incapable
of. And doesn't matter what scenario
people might throw at
you, you're incapable of doing certain
things. And that's where the freedom
comes from. you would have severed any
connection with those unh wholesome
intentions that you would have
maintained presently through not
practicing such reflections and clearing
out that that connection through the
possibilities of I could still act in
this or that way if I'm pushed or
pressed or or
similar. So when your mind is presently
not moved on account of any future
prospect and scenario you know like
marana maranaati the contemplation of
death all of these things it's exactly
the same purpose so when the mind is
completely not moved not frightened uh
not doubtful when the hindrances are
basically abandoned
uh that's how you will know oh I know
that now I'm free and that's what the
suta says he knows the mind is free he
knows he's free and he knows that his
mind is free he knows that he knows the
freedom. So it's understood on both
levels. So by introducing such scenario
you would be training your mind to stop
resisting them even on the level of such
possibilities. So
um so yeah there there's the question
that's also raised. It's like what is it
meant by that part in the suta where
says thus pursue pursued any deed done
to a limited extent no longer remains
there no longer stays there and it means
exactly this when you chain presently in
regard to future
possibility possibilities all the past
actions as
well have no bearing on you and that's
like that uh you know the the the drop
of dye in a in a sea it will not be able
to color the sea because the sea got
because the the amount of water is so
expanded in comparison to a drop of dye.
However, if you put a drop of dye in a
little teacup, it will be fully affected
by that. And that's the difference
between that limitlessness of the mind
that's developed through abandoning even
intentions towards ill will, intentions
towards hindrances, then even the most horrific
hindrances, then even the most horrific
act that you could have done in the
past will be a just drop of dye in the
sea. It will be it will be completely
well unperceivable basically have no
bearing. So I guess a few more examples
of the right reflecting as I said the
right contemplation of scenarios
um investigating your own
actions, investigating future actions,
investigating um as I said possible scenarios that
um as I said possible scenarios that
might make you or pressure you to act in
those future ways. and then like
drilling in the information to your own
cheetah that no those acts will not be
done even in such scenarios and then the
cheetah will be all tense and upset or
anxious and then you have to endure it.
It's like that's the training you you
present the perception to the animal and
you leave it there until the animal
comes down. If you take it beforehand
the message you convey is to the animal
is ah okay so my resistance to these
ideas and perceptions works cuz I
resisted and he got afraid and removed
it. Now he's not bringing it up. So I
keep doing that and that's how I won't
have to deal with it. And that's how
chitta remains
untamed. So contemplating non-ownership,
contemplating possibility of loss, all
the contemplations in the sutas, the the
repulsiveness, all that leads exactly to
the same way of containing your mind
within those
beneficial but highly unpleasant
perceptions. Um, but that's why again you can't
Um, but that's why again you can't
stress
this often enough. You need to have kept
the precepts and already formed some
sort of container. Otherwise, you might
end up like like those monks, they were
jumping off cliffs and stuff because
they couldn't bear it. So, be
careful. Um, okay. Okay. So, yeah, that the part
Um, okay. Okay. So, yeah, that the part
about the
meta, the the sort of
difference, well, the addition, let's
put it that way, that's uh that's
included in that uh agama that kind of
describes it a lot more um organically,
that development of metapractice as
opposed to just these these blocks of of
of
um memorized kind of lines during the
oral transmission that kind of lost all
the nuance. in
between. So
um it points out that that that agamma
part points out that one dwells day and
night practicing this. So it's not um
it's not a u a quick method. It's not
something you like just up to this
morning you were unestablished in your
behavior in precepts and then just
decide to okay now I abandon it and then
within five minutes you enter you
abandon hindrances because there's
nothing bothering you at the moment. Uh
you enter Janna or practice meta or
something. No, no, no. You practice day
and night because the
liability to the uh the the the
possibilities of acting in this way,
they're layers of it. So this these
these intentions to to harm, to engage
in to break the precepts, to to to all
these things, those
intentions, they can be very refined and
more and more refined the more you look
at them. So that's why you need to keep
bringing up scenarios and so on to see
if they still come up to see is there is
still leaning in that direction for the
mind to act in those ways if say you
didn't eat enough you didn't sleep
enough you were tired somebody upset you
uh experienced some fear some doubt um
so it's like you got to be purifying
that for who knows how long but that's
the training that's the
practice I mean again in the sutas you
find the same just it's usually
condensed to like one line when he says
says, "Oh, he dwells diligently
purifying his mind from our wholesome
states." And as I said, due to the whole
contemporary views through which people
read the sutas today, they tend to not
not even consider those lines that are
there and only consider the lines that
support the view of okay, so I do the I
do the method, I do the technique, I do
the practice, I do spreading of meta and
visualization of love and so on.
No, meta is the friendliness of an
animal that's unable to hate. Unable to
hate because you abandon every slightest
intention towards hate regardless of why
it would
happen. So in order to
practice and both both parallels pi and
nagama agree you have to abandon the
five hindrances.
hindrances.
So next time you're thinking that your
meta visualizations help you, ask
yourself, have you banned on hindrances
beforehand? If the answer is
no, they're not meta visualizations.
So yeah, so there's a few more
questions. Actually yeah I already answered this.
Actually yeah I already answered this.
So basically the question is like is it
correct to say that these successive
phenomena like joy, rapture,
tranquility, pleasure,
composure don't occur in say an hour of
right reflection after or after some
other practice but become the baseline
for one's being or experience on a
day-to-day basis as they cultivate and
progress towards braharas. Yeah,
absolutely. That's exactly how it is. uh
and as I said if you like with the help
of this agama you get that there are
like oh implications of like a a longer
period of time of development and then
you realize you could read Pali in that
way as well as I said there is a line
there that he says that he abandons he's
devoid of covetousness he's he's free
from it devoid of the hindrances it's
like that will take some time that will
take some understanding
wisdom So there's no like five minute
meta meditation basically. There's no
five minute any
meditation. Um so is it case that these successive
Um so is it case that these successive
uh beneficial qualities are born on
account of what's being abandoned rather
than tangible positive effort of
developing these qualities specifically
as I said patching them up through these
practices. And it's yeah of course it's
as I said it's through and as the suta
says it's through abandoning
intention to kill. So basically
abandoning intention of ill will and
harm let alone the
act. So through abandoning the intention
to go in the direction of harm and
killing animal becomes friendly. Not
through cultivating intention of
friendliness animal overrides its
liability to kill which is how people
today would like it to be.
Um so uh so what's the what's the
difference between Janna and developing
meta given that both sort of come on the
basis of um abandoning the the the
hindrances. So technically speaking I
would say um you develop
Janna towards the say internal aspect of
your point of view and the development
of Brahma viharas is toward external
aspect from your point of view. It's
just two opposite directions of the same
uh limitlessness that's that the mind is
developed. Uh obviously the the
difference is also like quite
specifically Janna would be outlined by
the um withdrawal by the separation
um withdrawal by the separation
segregation from the unh wholesome unh
wholesome states chief of which
sensuality. Meta is outlined by the unh
wholesome from withdrawal from unh
wholesome states chief of which this
deal will. So it kind of it depends
where where your animal is leaning to
more. If it's often leaning towards
[Music] uh
uh
sensuality, not so much towards ill
will, then yes, exactly. Through through
developing and practicing and
contemplating scenarios of a suba,
presenting it to your animal until it
learns to calm down and not react or not
kind of resort back to sensuality, you
are practicing
Janna. If your animal is prone to
hatred, ill will, irritation, and so
on, by contemplating scenarios that
would promp that up and taming your
animal within them, you're training it
to be friendly. Either way, the result
is the same. Limitlessness of the mind,
which completely um extinguishes you
from any connection with what has done
and what could be done. So, frees you
from karma basically.
Um so yeah it's also u one who pointed
out that
um says that it's the cheetah that
develops friendliness but the usual
practices today is just you use your own
thoughts mano images repeating phrases
and trying as I said trying to fabricate
stuff that would then magically just
make you cheer love
everybody
Um and uh the last I think it's the last
yes the last
question. So would successfully taking
on the precepts unconditionally as I
said you must for the sake of training
if you want to
train to the extent that you know that
you would actually never do these things
again because you see yourself uh for
for yourself now that they are unh
wholesome be sufficient for sapati
without undertaking the high level of
sense restraint. Yes. Exactly. So if you
take the
precepts in an unconditional
manner, see the dangers and the perils
of
sensuality sufficiently enough so that
your own cha is turned away from it even
if you haven't say fully understood it
and become anagami or something. But you
need to have had to abandon it equally
uh
unconditionally. not like I will refrain
from sensuality until I get the right
view and then go back to it. So the
entire training needs to be taken
unconditionally. So the eight precepts
or five precepts with
celibacy the speech as well that's why
often the the the precepts kind of from
the eight they just change into these
precept that include speech because the
all of the precepts are supposed to be
training precepts and all of them are
supposed to be training you in sotapati
if you take them on rightly that's why
in the sutras when it says uh disciple
established in virtue it's synonymous
with disciple being a sautana basically
that's what established in virtue means
doesn't mean I just happen to decide to
keep the precepts and I don't reflect
further or take them on uh indefinitely
but most of the time I don't break them
that's that's nowhere near any any
useful basis so the the question goes further
basis so the the question goes further
says I understand that some sense
restraint is necessary just to keep the
precepts of course but is it possible
for sapati to come before the official
sense restraint step on the gradual
training yeah yeah definitely
uh you Let the the the precepts of the
aggregate of virtue of knowing things
you won't do. You let that sink deep
enough into that animal for it to sort
of come to realize, oh yeah, actually
this is this is better for me as well.
That is the sort of party. Then that
animal can't turn against you. Can't
crave against things that that are
already understood as kind of
inaccessible. inaccessible to ownership,
inaccessible to craving, can't crave
towards pain. He recognized where it
comes from and he just cannot touch it.
And it was that inadvertent
touching of animal touching of the pain
that was causing the dooka, not the pain
itself, you know, like the the the two
arrows suta, the first one and the
second one.
So should one ever move on to the next
step of increased sense restraint before
they know for sure that they have
successfully taken on the precepts
unconditionally? Well, it's not going to
be that black and white. So you would
probably be moving sliding back, moving
forward, sliding
back while working on cementing the
unconditional determination behind the
precepts. Even if you fail and break
them, you really try to drill in that it
will never be done every single time.
So that then even when it's done that
weight of remorse sets in and actually
pushes uh pushes the mind in the
direction of growth whether the mind
wants it or not it will have to go that
way.